Shandra side welcome to concept and
coding and today we are going to start
with new topic in spring boot
microservices that is f client. We have
already covered rest template and rest
client and today this is the new topic
in the microservices communication. So
in future if we have to do microservices
communication most probably we are going
to use this only right. Why? you will
automatically get to know what are the
advantages for it right it's very easy
so let's start without wasting any
further time so fang is a declarative
remember this word it's a declarative
HTTP client developed by
Netflix declarative means we tell what
to do not how to do like so we are only
telling we want to communicate with X
service let's say we told but how
internally we have framework for it so
this is you can say that it has a
framework which handles how it will
communicate we only tell that yes our
service order service has to communicate
with let's say product service that's
all okay and how this framework will
handle it we will see that so in spring
boot fain capability is available via
spring
cloud open fain library. Okay. So the
capability which is developed by Netflix
in this fing framework is available in
spring cloud library in open fing
library. Okay. So now here one of the
thing is we need to know what is a
spring cloud
like so a spring cloud considered as a
set of tools and libraries which helps
to build distributed microservices. So
you know that when we develop a
distributed microservices lot of topics
or lot of features you can say that
required like service discovery uh
client side load balancing circuit
breaker API gateway distributed tracing
centralized configuration. So so many
things comes into the picture when we
talk about distributed micros service.
Okay.
So spring
cloud has seamless provides seamless
integration between all
these functionality. Okay. So that's why
in future one of the reason I told right
in future if we have to use microser
communication functionality we will make
use of open f library. Why? because one
thing is it is a part of a spring cloud
and it has seamless integration with all
of
this features service discovery feature
load balancing feature API gateway you
want.
So we have libraries for each one of it
and it all have very closely integrate
integrated with each other right so
we'll see that how it works in the
future but today let's keep focus on
open pane
library so that's the first thing we
have to do in the pom.xml example we
have to add the library. So we added the
library
of spring framework
cloud of open fin. Now here one thing
you notice that I haven't provided the
version. I haven't provided the version.
Why?
But I have added this dependency
management. Okay. So in dependency
management I have provided a spring
cloud dependency and give this version
but here I haven't provided the version
the reason being that the same thing I'm
coming back again in future we might
have to code for service discovery so we
have to add its library we have to code
for load balancing we want this feature
we have to add its library
so we are going to add multiple
libraries of spring cloud
Right? And so let's say I have one
library for open
fin. I have another library for uh
service discovery. I have another
library for load balancer. Okay. So all
its versions all its version should be
compatible with each other.
So either you write version here and in
future if you add more spring cloud
dependency let's say service discovery
so its version should be compatible with
whatever the version you are using for
the open fane okay so if in future you
are adding load balancer so its version
should be compatible with the service
discovery whatever the version you are
using and the version with the open fane
right so all should be compatible the
spring cloud version should be
compatible with each other. So I don't
want to do this, right? I don't want to
handle all this manually versions.
That's where the dependency management
comes into the picture. Okay, so a
spring cloud dependency we can use.
Okay, it's not like a mandatory. You can
use it or if you want you can put a
latest version here, right? But in
future you have to make sure that if you
are also using service discovery and you
are using its version so you need to
make sure that both these version are
compatible to each other. But if you
don't want all this headache and you
don't want to manage it manually we can
leave up to spring boot itself like we
are using spring cloud dependency. Now
Maven will take care that all the
dependency it will bring in which are
compatible right. So even if you are
using service discovery we will not
write version. If you're using load
balancer we will not write its version.
So proper version will be automatically
added by Maven. Okay. With the help of
this dependency management. Okay. So the
first thing we have added is dependency
in our pom.xml.
Now this is our
requirement. We have an order service
which is running on port number
8081. And this auto service need to
invoke the product service like we have
seen in the previous rest client also
which is running on localhost
8082. So now what how this communication
will happen in fain client. So the first
here if you
see we are writing an interface. So I am
writing in the order service I need to
communicate with product service right.
So I'm writing one interface and give it
a name product
client. And here if you
see I have written one method
right get product by
id. What is the path variable? I give
provided the path variable id and get
mapping. So it's just like how we used
to define in the controller. If you see
that generally in controller we define
any API right. Similarly like this I am
defining here. So what exactly I'm doing
here. So here if you
see actually I am telling that which
endpoint I have to
communicate of the product service. So
product service has this / product / id.
So that's your get call. I want to make
a get call get mapping get call of this
API. Okay. And I you can give a method
and this
id is nothing but a path variable. So
whatever the id it will come it
will replaced here. Okay. So very very
similar to what we generally define in
the controller. Okay. And it's since
it's an interface we don't have to
implement
it. So see this thing we are not writing
any logic. We just told what to call or
what to do but not how we just only told
that yes we have to invoke this API /
product/ ID okay and this ID is replaced
by this path variable okay and how it
has to be invoked we haven't provided
any
implementation okay and on the top of
this interface is this is very important
that we have annotated with at the rate
fing client that this is considered this
as a fing client because
this spring uh fing framework frame uh
fing client framework
internally has to provide an
implementation for this right okay
because not for each normal interface
whatever the method you will write
automatically its implementation will
happen No. So for this interface we have
to annotate with fing client. We have to
give any arbitrary name. You can give
any arbitrary name. So I have just
provided like this uh name of this fing
client. Let's say product service. You
can give any name. Okay. And the URL
it's like the base URL. So this is
considered as a base URL. Local host
8082. Right? Host and the
port. Okay. So this is the URL and I am
currently reading it from
application.properties. So in the
application.properties I have provided
this link
faint.client.prouct service. URL you can
give anything. Okay you can give
anything and here I have provided the
host and the port. So this
URL
this base URL will get replaced
here. Okay. So first thing first what we
have done is we have created an
interface annotated with faint line.
Okay. And there we have provided the
base URL and we have written a method
right and provided like which exact API
we have to invoke. Okay. So you can see
that it has a direct mapping here with
the product service. So product service
has this API. So we want to invoke this.
So that's where what we have provided
here. Similarly, it's it is get mapping.
So here also it is get mapping. Okay.
The endpoint which we have to invoke.
Okay. So this endpoint for this one get
product endpoint is / product / id. So
that's here. And this ID is replaced by
this path variable. Okay. So this things
will get more clear. But first thing is
we have to create such
interface. No implementation is
required.
Okay. Application.properties. We have
already seen that this base URL either
you can hardcode it or if you don't want
to hardcode it, you can read it from
application.properties like this. You
can give any URL which you any path
which you want it. It's not like you
have to like follow this only
fang.client client dot you can give
anything whatever the uh name you want
to
give the third thing is controller now
here if you see in the
controller I am doing auto wiring of
this product client I am doing an auto
wiring of this product line client so
product line I am doing auto wire okay
and in this order API let's say I have
to invoke
the product API in this order a in this
order method I have to invoke the
product API so I will use this client
product client dot I will call this
method get product by ID and let's say
whatever the ID you want to pass you can
pass it or you can pass any value
okay and that's
all that's all so here if you see you
will get a response so what is the
response you expecting a response of a
string. So here I am catching the
response in a string only and I'm just
printing response from product API call
is whatever I will get here order call
successful and last thing very small
thing but very important is in your
application in your order service
application you just have to enable the
f clients like at the rate enable f
clients by default it's false so we once
we write this annotation what happen is
it will tell spring boot to scan for
interfaces annotated with faint line.
Okay, without
this spring boot will not even go and
scan
this interfaces which are annotated with
faint client. No. So we have to use this
annotation and only after that you can
say that f client is enabled in our
code. Okay. And after that only our
spring boot will start looking for this
annotation. All the interfaces with this
annotation. So four things we are doing.
We are writing the interface. Don't
worry if you uh haven't understood much
about it
currently for now. Just understand like
what all things required to make a
communication using faint client. First
thing is we need to create one
interface. That's all. No
implementation. Second thing is
application.properties properties not
mandatory either you can hardcode the
URL here or it's better if you use the
application.properties properties to
define the base URL so that it is easier
to change in
future. The third thing is like wherever
whatever the service layer or wherever
you want to invoke the product API so
you have to auto it and just invoke the
method and the response you will got and
just use it like you how you wanted to
use and the fourth is that you have to
enable it in your spring application.
Okay. Now if you start and invoke the
API here if you see order call
successful this one order call
successful and it should print this
system do.print len. So here if you see
it is printing. So it is invoking the
endpoint product endpoint. It is
invoking right fetch the product detail.
So this one is returning this one. So it
returned
this it catch it here and then printed
it.
So here if you see how easy it is
to make a microser
communication I haven't written anything
like uh dot even let's say even in the
rest client rest client is also easy
right fluent API like but here I have to
tell I have to tell like how to
communicate but here if itself I haven't
done any
implementation I I haven't done any any
implementation. All I have done is which
API I have to talk
to. Okay. So one question definitely
comes to your mind is
how how this
declarative thing work. So here if you
see the very basic question which I'm
saying which comes to your mind is that
hey Shange we have created an
interface product client annotated with
faint client. That's okay. But still we
haven't provided any implementation for
this method. Okay. But in the order
controller we are doing auto
wiring. If you see this we are doing
auto wiring right? Auto
wired. How
come? How come I am able to auto when
you are doing auto wire means an object
is present. Okay. So interface you can't
create an object right. So somebody has
provided its implementation and that
implementation objects comes here but
how I haven't provided its
implementation.
So who has provided it? The fing client
framework
how see this it's not easy but let me
try to explain in a very simple method
what happened in the behind. So it will
make you things clear and you don't have
to muck this up that okay this this
should be done like this only. So let's
see the flow then it will give you a
very intuitive like how to use this f
client and how it's actually might be
internally working. So now let's say
that we have done till here like we have
written only interface with f client not
implementation we have autowiring it
right. So when we have started the
application right when we started the
application what would happen since we
have provided this annotation at the
rate enable f
clients it will scan for f clientline
interface that's the first thing it will
do it will scan all the interfaces which
are annotated with f client okay now for
each interface it will invoke this
reflective fing class and in that There
is a method called new instance. So for
each
interface it invoked this method which
is present in reflective fing class.
Okay. Now this is very important class
because it does three things. The first
thing which it does
is create an object of method
handler. Okay. So for each meth so now
let's say that for each interface now in
this interface interface one let's say
it has two method method one method two
so for each method it will run and it
will create an object of method
handler now what is method
handler method handler object holds
complete info that is parsed from a
method and its
annotation And these all info is needed
to execute the HTTP requests. So what
generally happen is now from each
method it do a
parsing okay it understand its
annotations right
and it will update all these fields like
target URL. So target URL is nothing but
a base URL plus relative path. So here
if you see that in the your interface at
the rate fank client we provided the URL
right. So this is your base URL and your
relative path is in the at the rate get
mapping we were providing / product /
id. So this is your relative path. This
is your relative path. Okay. So this
variable got filled up. HTTP method get
put or post that is derived from
annotation like add the get mapping. Add
the post mapping.
Similarly, header info. Header info is
derived from add the rate request header
if there is any. Similarly, HTTP client
variable. So, by default, fang client is
using HTTP URL connection. If you
remember the rest template, it is also
using HTTP URL connection. But if you
want to use different let's say okay
HTTP Apache HTTP client, we can
configure it. Okay. But this is the
default HTTP URL connection it uses is
if you want to change we can change it.
Okay. Then encoder. So encoder is like
convert the request body from Java
object to HTTP format like JSON. So
consider this in the
rest client and rest template we will
call it serialization des serialization
right. So similarly in the faint client
it's like encoder decoder like Java
object to JSON and decoder is like once
the response coming so from let's say
JSON to Java object okay so it has
provided its own default implementation
is there it uses uh Jackson but if you
want to configure ourself we can also do
that so it's a configurable okay so this
all fields get filled up actually it is
all present into method handler so from
each meth method for each method this
object is getting created. Okay.
Similarly, we have error encoder. Error
error decoder. Error decoder is like if
you remember from the previous video
rest client, we have something called
exception handler. So here it is
something called very similar error
decoder. So if any exception comes 4xx
or 5xx how to handle it. Okay. So it has
it provide us a default implementation
but if you want to configure it we can
do our own implementation also we have
to do I will show you the example also
don't worry about that similarly logger
and retry so we are calling an API if
any connection timeout happen how many
times we have to retry two times three
times so it is also in our control it
also provide default implementation and
also it's a configurable we can provide
our own implementation also so Here in
the short if I have to summarize method
handler is method handler is something
which is derived from the method right
like uh its annotation and it's uh you
can say that
signature right and all these fields get
derived from that particular method and
all these fields are very very
important which is needed to execute the
actual HTTP request.
Okay. So for each for each method it
creates a map like okay this is the
method let's say this is the method
right where it g yeah this is get
product by id so this is the method this
is the method
handler okay similarly if you have two
methods so in the map you have both the
details okay so first thing is for each
method method handler is created which
is derived the info from parsing the
method
Okay. And these all info are important
which is required to actually make an
HTTP call and handle the response.
Right? Everything all the info is
present here. Now once you created this
method handler and put it into the map
what it does is it create an object of
invocation handler. Very important.
Right? So consider it as a
bridge. Right? I will tell you like how
it is act as a bridge. But the next step
which it does is create an object of
invocation handler and whatever the map
we have created here right that is
stored here inside this. Okay. So this
also has this
map method comma method handler. Okay.
So the object what we have created at
the first step that is stored here now.
Okay. So that is the first thing we
create an object of it and populated
whatever we have uh derived in the step
one. Here we have update this populate
this object map method handler and this
also has one method invoke. This
invocation handler has one method invoke
which act as a
bridge which act as a bridge between
proxy implementation and the method
handler. Okay, don't worry about this.
Now I will tell you how it acts as a
bridge. But for now only remember this
two things that invocation handler has
this info like it has the map like for
each method what is the method handler
and it has one method called invoke
which act as a bridge between the proxy
implementation and the method
handler. Now what is proxy
implementation? So that's where the
third step
is. Okay. Once we complete this third
step right you will the whole picture
will get clear how it is how this act as
a bridge how the
flow total flow goes right that will all
clear. Now the third step is what this
new instance. So first in so first step
easy it create a method handler by
parsing the method. Second step also
easy. It create an object of invocation
handler and whatever the map we have
created it will populate inside its
object also. The third step is it uses a
dynamic proxy to create a runtime
implementation of our interface. So it
created a dynamic proxy. If you remember
dynamic proxy is used to create a
runtime like it create a code for us at
runtime. So I was so that question right
we haven't provided the implementation
but we are able to do the auto wiring
means somebody is implementing it right
that's where this third step it uses a
dynamic proxy to create a runtime
implementation so this is this is just a
demo class nowhere in the spring cloud
openf library you wouldn't find this
class this is just my understanding
that what dynamic proxy might be
creating implementation for that.
Okay. So there is no such class like
fing product client proxy. It is just my
understanding and demo of how dynamic
proxy would have implemented our
interface product client. So we have
this interface right product client. How
this dynamic proxy would have created
what code it might have written. So that
is just my understanding. If you go and
look, you won't find this class. Okay.
So, this
is
dynamically
created by
proxy.
Okay. So, if you have to just understand
what dynamic proxy, how it will generate
the class, what that class going to look
like. So, this is just a demo. So, let's
say that it will create any name like
this is just a demo name. It implements
our interface. Okay. And here if you see
it has
handler. Now since it is implementing
our interface, it has to provide a
implementation for this method get
product by id. So that's where we
provide an implementation. Now here what
it will do is it just call handler. What
is the invocation handler? Right? It
will just invocation handler dot
invoke. Right? and pass
this
method.
Okay, so we get the method, right? Get
product by ID. So we get the method
detail from here. Get product by ID.
Okay, so it just invoke the handler. So
now you will get to know that what
generally happen
is now let's say that in we are invoking
from the controller class of order
controller. Now let's say I am
calling product
client my interface right product client
dot get
product by
id something let's say
one now I am invoking this method now
I'm trying to invoke this method now
what would happen is this class will
intercept it this is the class which
dynamically has has been created. Okay.
So now this is the implementation for
that my interface method. Right? So this
will intercept it. So control will come
here. What it will do is it will fetch
the method like we can find it like get
product by ID. Right? We will get its
method detail. We have already covered
this in Java, right? How this reflection
works. So it will take out the method
object like we can easily take this out
for each method. Now it is now from this
method we can take out the meta data
what is the return type what is the
parameter right is this public or
private etc etc so now this I can get
all the information about my get product
by id method and now I am calling this
handler which is invocation handler so
it will call this invoke method now if
you remember I told you that this invoke
method act as a bridge between the proxy
implementation and the method handler.
So now I got this from proxy
implementation. What it will do is it
provided us me the method right this
method. So for it has this variable map
method comma method handler. So from
this
method from this map it will take out
the handler. Okay. for this method. What
is the method handler once it got the
handler? It call its
invoke. Okay. So what it does is it act
as a bridge the call which is coming
from proxy
implementation. From here I just got
that
method from here. This map I take out
that what is the method handler for that
particular method. And for that method
handler I invoke the its invoke method.
So method handler also has this invoke
method. So method handler has all these
fields plus also has invoke method. Now
here if you see this method handler
invoke method is actually
creating the request object HTTP
request and then ultimately executing
it.
It's actually making a HTTP call here.
So this is the place where exact call
will happen.
Execute. Okay. So you got the flow and
got the answer like what internally
happened even we haven't provided the
implementation we are able to autoirate
properly because of this
flow. Okay.
how this invocation handler act as a
bridge between these two. So if you go
through this flow again you will get to
know and you will find your answer that
what internally happening behind this
declarative. So we only told what to do
but how internally this code is
determining it is doing parsing from the
annotation it determine what's the
target URL header info client encoder
decoder. So it if you haven't provided
it it took the default if you provide it
it will fill it. We will see that
example how to provide all of this value
also. Okay. And then how proxy
implementation going to look like and
how invocation handler act as a
bridge.
Okay. So this is just one example where
I'm trying to use as much annotation
possible. So here the same I am creating
an interface product line annotated with
f client. provide any name to your f
client like I just give any arbitrary
name I provided product service URL
either you can hardcode it or you can
read it from application.properties
properties. Now this is one method. Get
product by ID. It's a get call. This is
the relative path which I want to hit.
And this ID is generally read from this
path variable. Like this ID which I'm
get, it's going
to update it into this path variable.
Similarly, I can write more at the putut
mapping the same value like what is the
relative path and the consumes
application dot JSON means what is my
request body content is it is
JSON. So here I have provided path
variable like this id whatever I will
get it should be updated into this path
variable plus there is a request param
also like after that question mark
send mail equals to true false okay so
request param will get added after this
header would get added I just added some
uh custom header okay so at the request
header this API also has a body So
request body. Okay. So I have provided
the body also. So in the product
application in the product application
which is running on 8082. So it has if
you see this put mapping right they have
one corresponding endpoint which I want
to invoke. So it also has at the rate
putut mapping right. So it also has like
/ product / updates / id. So that's what
I wanted to hit. Okay. Now here if you
see that one to one mapping is not
mandatory. Okay. Spring boot will take
care of like uh passing the values
according to annotation. So here if you
see my first is let's say path variable.
Second is request param. Third is
request header. Fourth is request body.
Here ordering is different. First is
path variable. Second is request body.
And here it is last. Here it is second.
But still it's okay. It will work fine
because spring boot while creating
invoking this right it will based on
this annotation it
will assign it will fill the
values. Okay. So one to one mapping is
not required. With the help of
annotations our finline framework will
get to know that the order.
Okay. So very very very similar to how
in controller we write a method, right?
Similarly like this we just have to
write like whatever is the endpoint we
have to
invoke. So now the next thing is like
encoder decoder in the f client. So till
now we haven't provided encoder decoder.
Okay. Generally if you see that in the
rest line it's generally serialization
des serialization okay we can provide
custom
implementation and here if you
see when the method handler object is
created it has an field for encoder and
decoder okay generally if you don't
provide
it the by default it will use and I told
you it's a configurable we can provide
our own implement mentation how do we
want to encode how do we want to decode
so that's where we will see that like
how it's
happening so what does encoder means
converts a Java object into a request
body okay because ultimately we have to
send the let's say JSON so we can't send
Java object so serialization should have
happened say that so now here you can
say that here in the Spain client we are
calling it encoder where we are
converting a Java object to respective
request body let's say JSON similarly
decoder once the response come we have
to convert it to a Java object okay so
that's what it generally called as
decoder right convert the HTTP response
body say it's coming in JSON we have to
convert it to the Java object right if
you remember in the rest line it's like
serialization And in the d serialization
we were doing manually we were reading
the stream and converting it to an
object right the same thing here also it
does
internally. So if you remember
this method
handler which I showed you here right
where ultimately uh it create a request
and invoke execute and decode it method
handler.
So where exactly this encoder decoder
comes into the picture. So encoder if
you go this where we are building the
request right if you internally debug it
okay you will find that it is doing
encoder.enccode it calling this method
okay and it pass the body. So internally
this method it make use of encoder by
default internally it uses Jackson and
in the request template not rest
template request template and in the
request template body would be put as
raw JSON right so now here if you see
that this encoder dot encode this
encoder is an
interface
this encoder is an interface So there is
a default implementation available.
Okay. I think you can double check.
There is something called a spring
encoder. I'm not sure. You can double
check. So there is this encoder is an
interface and there is a default
implementation I think is spring encoder
which provides an implementation which
internally use JSON and parse this.
Okay. it pars the body Java object and
convert it to a raw JSON and put it into
the request template
body. Similarly, where the decode will
happen like once you get the response.
So this internally if you go to execute
and decode internally this method make
use of decoder. So you will find this
code decoder dot
decode. Okay. Similarly here decoder is
an interface and it has like a
spring decoder class which implement
this and it again uses JSON. So there it
read the byte stream and convert it to a
java object like we used to do in rest
client. Okay but it's all now abstracted
to us. It just like we have to go and
see what where exactly it
happen.
So we can provide our own implementation
here like we can implement the encoder
and provide our own implementation here
custom implementation here. Similarly
inside a decoder we can write our own
class which implements it and write our
own custom decoder. So that's what I am
going to do. Now if you want to write
our custom encoder decoder what we can
do. So the first thing
is I am creating an interface product
line all exactly it is no change but
remember uh see this here I am
annotating this interface with fing
client giving it an arbitrary name URL
which is the base URL. Now this is the
new like I am providing a configuration
and I am writing new configuration
product client config. So see this now
in your application let's say this is
our order
application order application might have
to communicate with product application
product
APIs let's say there is some other
microser let's say sales
APIs some other microser let's let's say
user user
APIs okay there could be different
microservices this is let's say microser
service one, micros service 2, micros
service 3, different different
microservices. Okay. So when I am
talking with this product
APIs, I want configuration specific to
this
only. When I talk with sales APIs, I
want configuration specific for this.
Maybe its encoder, its decoder for
example, its
timeout, read
timeout, connection timeout is different
than sales APIs, right? So we can easily
do this like so here in the f client you
can provide a configuration and the
class. So this class now belongs to this
fang client
only. Okay. So this interface which is
product
client okay and here I have provided the
configuration product client config. So
all these APIs which you will provide
under this
interface this configuration would be
applied. Similarly you can have
different like user client or sales
client different client interface and
you can provide different configuration.
So their configuration would be present
for their APIs. Okay. So there is no
impacting between each other. Okay. So
that is one of the another advantage
like it's so clean that uh we can manage
the configuration between different
clients easily. So this is let's say my
one client product client sales client
user client right I can easily manage
their configuration separately from each
other. Okay. So the first thing is
mentioning the configuration for this
product client product line config.class
class and that's where in the created
one class product client config
annotated with at the rate configuration
okay I'll come to this again so first
thing is configuration we have to
provide one config class for this
product now here if you see I am writing
my custom product encoder so I told you
encoder is an interface we just have to
implement our custom interface so that's
what I did implements the encoder
So once we implement this interface we
have to provide the functionality of
this method and here I'm just simply
converting an object to JSON very simple
method just for testing like demo. So
I'm what I'm using an object mapper and
converting it to a raw JSON string and
inside the request template I'm putting
this raw
JSON. Okay, most similarly the default
also doing the same thing. I don't have
to provide a custom implementation for
this because default also almost does
the same thing. The spring encoder also
does the mostly same thing. But just for
testing, if you have some different
logic, you can add here. Similarly,
decoder I have provided my decoder.
Product line decoder implements this
decoder. Now I have to provide this
implementation and here I am reading the
stream and from this stream I'm
converting it to this type whatever the
type which is coming. Okay. So generally
this type is like that return type of
the
method. Okay. Now we just have to create
an object of this. Right. So in the
configuration I have just created a bean
for this two encoder and
decoder. Okay. So now what would happen
is in our code whenever this encoder
object is required right so this would
be used and decoder this would be used
client
decoder okay and similarly on the same
path itself all the custom different
custom implementation which we have to
do is right we will do that right like
error decoder in fain
client in rest client you Remember it's
called as exception handling. When 4xx
happen, when 5xx happen, how to handle
the exception. So it is used to handle
non2x status code like 4xs, 5xs. So here
if you see this is the method handler
code. Okay. So here it is running
execute and decode. Right? So internally
once it get the
response once it get the response it
analyze the response and if there is an
error if it is not to access what it
will do is it will call error decoder
dot
decode okay error decoder dot decode. So
again
error
decoder you can say that it's an
interface and it
has a decode
method. Okay. So there is an
implementation present at it. So error
decoder class. So here if you see error
decoder I think it's an interface. You
can double check it. It's an
interface and decode has a default
implementation present. We can check
that error decoder.
error
decoder. It's an
interface. So it's an interface and it
has provided us the decode method. Okay.
So it has uh it has a default
implementation for this error decoder.
So default
implementation it is now implementing
it. Okay. So this is
error decoder.
Error
decoder dot default
actually. Okay, error decoder dot
default. Okay, so default is the one
which implementing this
error decoder class and provides an
implementation of this method. So here
if you see what it is doing is simply is
that it is returning the fain
exception. Okay. So in the fain
exception it include status code
response body and header. So generally
this is how your exception going to look
like. If any exception happen right it's
going to look like this bad request fain
exception bad request 400 and your body
if there is any error that will also get
included.
Okay. But here if you see that is not
very much clear and you get a
requirement that hey I need to handle it
differently. I don't want this kind of
exception to be thrown. Okay. So what
you can do right the same thing error
decoder right we
can write our own implementation. We can
write our own
implementation. That's what I'm going to
do. The first thing is
first whatever the interface we have
created this is the endpoint which we
have to
invoke and for this product client I
have annotated this interface with the f
client annotation and I have provided
its configuration very very specific for
this product product line client
configuration. Now I am writing my error
decoder and implements the interface
error decoder. Now I have to
implement the method decode method. Now
whatever the logic which you want. So I
am very very simple I am doing is like
if a status code is 4xx throw this
custom exception. If a status code is
5xs throw this custom exception. I am
writing this custom exception. Right? Uh
we have seen this in rest client itself.
We can write our own exception and we
have already seen in Java tutorials
also. Now how we can write our own
exception. So this is just a very simple
right we can add a status code message
proper whatever we wanted it. So this is
just a very very basic like what
exception we want to throw. Okay. And uh
if it is not 4xs if it is not 5xs and if
you want to handle the default the again
I am creating a default. I told you
right
here it is error decoder dot default
class which is implementing it. So
ultimately I will call this it will
handle it.
Okay, if I am not able to handle it,
ultimately I'll pass it to the default
decode. Hey, you handle
it. Okay, and in this configuration I
just have to return a object of mine
error decoder which is the bean of error
decoder. Okay. So now
[Music]
in code whenever this error decoder doc
decode will get invoked it will invoke
mine this class not the default
one okay and here if you see now this is
how the exception will be thrown bad
request exception client error because
I'm throwing
this this is just an example we can have
it a better way like you want it this is
just an example like whatever your
custom exception If you want you can
throw it like
way. Another thing we have in something
called retryer in f client. So here if
you see this is what method handler code
is right method
handler. So here if you see any like
here it is ultimately it's do execute
and decode. Now let's say any connection
timeout happen. So some it will catch
it. Okay. And then it will check hey
continue or
propagate. Continue means if there is a
retry attempt left go and hit it one
more time. Try executing it one more
time. Else propagate it. Let it catch by
error
decoder. Okay. So what's the default
behavior? Till now we haven't defined
any retryer. So what's the default
behavior for the retryer? So retry only
happen first thing is let's before goes
to the default uh we need to understand
that retry only happen when there is
connection timeout and network related
exception that IO exception or something
so it should be a retriable exception
not like anything if it is 4xx or
5xs at the start itself it will directly
go to error decoder itself only if it is
retrial exceptions
S it will try to retry. It will try to
make an another attempt. If all the
attempt finish then error decoder
ultimately will get invoked to handle
the
exception. Okay. So here if you see the
default which it's closed that retry
clone. So here the default one is it is
the default which implements the
retryer.
It has this configuration. Maximum
attemp is five. Five times it will do
attemp 100 millisecond. This 100 is the
initial weight time call. So let's say
you first time you are making an
immediate attempt. First time I'm
calling a product API. Product API
immediate attempt. Let's say connection
timeout happen. So try two will happen
only after 100 seconds like so wait okay
now let's say that after 100 second try
to happen that also connection timeout
happen now try three will wait for 200
millisecond so double so it will double
each time so the wait time get double
each time okay so try four 400 try 5
800 okay and the max cap is currently
it's put the max is 1 second so Maximum
only is 1 second it can wait not more
than that after 1 second if it is let's
say try six it will not like okay 1 1600
millcond no maximum is 1 second now
after 1 second it will make try six try
7 try 8 how many whatever the attempt
left so this is the maximum wait time
this is the you can say that start
initial weight time and it doubled with
each
retry Okay. So this is the default
implementation and there is something
called retryer dot never retry this is
also present if you don't want to retry
itself not even default five times
itself because default behavior is it
will retry five uh not retry maximum
attempt is four. So one is actual call
and then you can say that four is the
retry. So total five attempts. So if you
only want one attempt itself right you
can use never retry retry dot never
retry. So in the
configuration I am returning a bean of
retry but called it never retry. So we
already have uh uh present in the retry
class itself. So like it has the default
right. Similarly it has uh never retry
where it has only one attempt.
Okay, the actual immediate attempt only
no
retries. But if you want custom
implementation, okay, that we can do
also the same thing. Custom
implementation is like we will make use
of configuration very specific to our
interface product
line.
Now use case
one, I only want to customize the
attempt initial time or the maximum
period time. That's all.
rest the
logic rest the logic I can make use of
the default
one what is the rest of the logic like
hey if your
attempt is increase the max attempt then
you don't have to go and retry you have
to throw exception like all this thing
so I don't want to do all those logic
all I want to do is configure this
values then what I do is I can write my
custom retryer extend the
default. Okay, extend the default and in
the constructor I pass the super this
different values whatever I
want. Okay, and all the method which it
has make use of default only. But if you
want full control then you write your
custom entry and implement the retry
itself interface itself. So now you have
to implement the method
also. So this is dot default is not an
interface. It's a class. So I'm
extending it. Okay. So this continue or
propagate actually it would be already
present into the default. All I am
providing is different value of the
configuration. But if you implement this
interface you have to provide the
implementation for this method also. So
now you have to like full control what
is the atam max atam. In this method you
have to like I'm just using as a dummy
like uh if attemp is greater than equals
to max attempt means all the attempts
are finished then you have to throw
exception otherwise do attemp plus then
you have to sleep it. So this is I have
hardcoded sleep for 100 millisecond okay
but generally the logic is there like
double every time in the default. So
like if you want a complete logic you
can complete uh you can say that control
over the implementation you can do this
otherwise you if you want a control over
this values you can use
default okay once this is done and here
if you see in the configuration in the
bean I'm just returning creating my
retry object and returning the bean of
this
one okay and also
Last but not the least during start and
every time we are saying that whenever
we are creating an
interface we are annotating it with
faint client and giving it a arbitrary
name like say product hyphen
service where this actual name is
helpful to
us. So this is one like you can say that
it will come into an handy during
configuration in application.properties.
So here if you
see if I want to set a request and
connection time out only for product
service faint client only for
this only for this faint client. How I
would set this for this faint client
with the help of this name because I
have
gi client right and this f client is
there in the product client. So I am
providing this configuration in the
application.properties. Hey fane
do.client
dotconfig dot the name of the f client
connect timeout is
this.
Similarly read timeout this. So now this
connection timeout and read timeout is
very very specific for this fain client
product service f client.
this if you have multiple let's say uh
sales client user client multiple
clients you can have different different
different connection timeout read
timeout for them I can have let's say
user hyphen service I can give different
timeout for them okay I have like order
service I can provide different timeout
for them okay so this is one of the
advantage here also for each different
client wise
I can very easily configure the
timeouts. Okay. But let's say you have a
requirement that
hey same timeout I want to apply for
all. Okay. Then you just use default.
When you use default it ultimately
applies to all like all fan clients all
the fan clients. Uh this will get
applied. This timeout, connection
timeout and read timeout will get
applied if you use default. If you want
to use very specific for
your F client like only for product
service fine only for
this use a specific name.
Okay. And ultimately now at this point
of time you should be able to know that
these configuration values connection
time out read timeout ultimately all
this somewhere will get set into
this this all somewhere there might be
some variables which get filled up using
this
configurations. Okay. because there are
other variables fields also that's why I
put etc. So there could be some other
field which is like connection time out
read timeout what is the values it might
reading from the application.properties
properties. So, but ultimately very
important here is method handler. It has
all the variables fields which is
important to make a connection and also
it has a method which actually does all
the things create a request execute
handle
everything. Okay. So I have explained
you all the flow and I hope if you go it
one more time or you try to implement it
by your hand the things will get clear
the flow will get clear to you that
how these things are
working. Okay. So if you have any doubt
let me know in the comment section we
can discuss further. Thank you guys.
Bye.